Antonio Sanso: Matteo.
Antonio Sanso: Hi Matteo.
Antonio Sanso: Can you guys hear me?
Matteo Vena | Riva Labs: Citi Sentiamo Tuccicenti.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, yeah, good. Alessandro.
Alessandro Baiocchi: I…
Antonio Sanso: Hi, Toma.
Antonio Sanso: Today might be a quiet call, but as usual, we start a couple of minutes after.
Antonio Sanso: Just in case there's some late joiner.
Antonio Sanso: You see my…
Antonio Sanso: screen.
Matteo Vena | Riva Labs: Yes, we do.
Antonio Sanso: Okay, perfect.
Alessandro Baiocchi: Yes.
Antonio Sanso: It's still not 3 o'clock, we start around… now it's 3, we start around 3.02, as usual.
Matteo Vena | Riva Labs: Okay.
Antonio Sanso: I usually put a reminder on Twitter about the call.
Antonio Sanso: I mean, the last occurrences I did. Today, I didn't do it on purpose, because it's pretty quiet.
Antonio Sanso: There's no presentation, so it might be a bit more quiet than usual.
Antonio Sanso: And yeah, I was more looking for more discussions, but
Antonio Sanso: It might be a quick one today.
Antonio Sanso: Right, let's start, and I guess that today's gonna really be a quiet one. Welcome to the Post Quantum Transaction Signature Breakout Room number 16. Today is September 30.
Antonio Sanso: And, yeah, I, again, I don't have anything in the agenda today, apart the testnet. That's why I didn't put too much noise into the various channels, like Twitter and so on.
Antonio Sanso: for the few people that are here, and I think this is more for you, Tomas.
Antonio Sanso: Because, the other day, I see Matteo, Matteo, and Alessandro, and Benedikt, they didn't know about it. We launched a testnet.
Antonio Sanso: Daisuke.
Antonio Sanso: And, yeah, thanks to Julius, Natira de Riva Labs, and Emil, and the DevOps at EF.
Antonio Sanso: We have… launched two versions so far. The first one is version 01, that was.
Antonio Sanso: Non-native account abstraction, so ERC 4337.
Antonio Sanso: And, signature, this is some variant of Sphinx.
Antonio Sanso: And.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, we actually managed, again, thanks to RivaLabs and Julio, new version 0.2 that you can choose at the beginning between
Antonio Sanso: ERC4337 and NATIVE, so friend transaction, there's EIP8141.
Antonio Sanso: That will be Stefano, that will be in Hegota.
Antonio Sanso: And now it's here where I was actually looking for help, because we're starting with the next phase, and you basically want to implement
Antonio Sanso: 8288, so aggregated… aggregation of the signatures in the mempool. We have a version of, Lean VM and Lean Sphinx, in… by Emil, and some patch from the RivaLabs people.
Antonio Sanso: And,
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, here is where I was planning to have some kind of discussion, and if someone wants to help, so I see a part of the people already helping, I see you, Stefano, and…
Antonio Sanso: I don't know if you are interested in giving a help into this effort.
Antonio Sanso: And in case we're gonna discuss Stefan left, so it's only us now. Oh, no, it's here, Stefan, or Tomas as well.
Antonio Sanso: If you guys are into…
Antonio Sanso: Help him to this, we can have a discussion now.
Antonio Sanso: Otherwise, I mean, let's discuss about it in any case, right? So I don't know if any of you is familiar with A2A10, but- Yes.
Stefano: Sorry, Antonio, sorry, since I was a few, a couple of minutes late, so I missed the beginning of this part. So if you could like briefly summarize what the.
Antonio Sanso: help.
Stefano: Apologies.
Antonio Sanso: No worries, I mean, let's move to the beginning, actually. It's really pretty quick presentation, because I don't have anything in the agenda. I was just, like, introducing the testnet.
Antonio Sanso: And again, the credits are of these guys. So far, we had the version number 01 that had non-native account abstraction, so ERC4337 with some variant of Sphinx. Then we already deployed Testnet version 02.
Antonio Sanso: where you can choose between non-native, so still ERC4337, and frame transaction, and it's already up and running. And then we are moving toward the third phase, this version 03, but at this point, we are into Virgin territory.
Antonio Sanso: We know that we want some kind of aggregation. We have a version of Lean Sphinx and LeanVM that aggregates signatures, and Emil was so nice that he did a version of LeanVM that aggregates the same parameter we are using Testnet.
Antonio Sanso: So, I'm looking for people that are helping. So far, the people helping here are the Riva Labs guys, they're on the call.
Antonio Sanso: Giulio and Emil, if someone else wants to help.
Antonio Sanso: On this effort, we can start discussing, actually, now.
Antonio Sanso: How this will look like.
Antonio Sanso: And, actually, let me try an experiment. Let me open the… for once.
Antonio Sanso: Let me try to open the…
Antonio Sanso: The whiteboard, and let's try this experiment of discuss stuff here, why not?
Antonio Sanso: So… Because, again, it's really… this is really, like, virgin territory.
Antonio Sanso: And,
Antonio Sanso: So, maybe it might be a good idea to have people help. I don't find a whiteboard here, I don't know why not. Let's let me add it.
Antonio Sanso: Whiteboard.
Antonio Sanso: Not sure why the whiteboard is not showing.
Antonio Sanso: Really found me.
Antonio Sanso: Whiteboard… Usually, there's integrated whiteboards I use all the time.
Antonio Sanso: But I don't know why it doesn't show here.
Antonio Sanso: Hold on a second.
Antonio Sanso: I really have no clue why there is no debt.
Antonio Sanso: The whiteboard's here, let's see here… Transcripts…
Antonio Sanso: Hmm.
Stefano: You could always just, point the camera to a Physical whiteboard, then.
Stefano: Yeah, well…
Antonio Sanso: Sure, I mean… Let me find it.
Stefano: That's always the backup low-tech option.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, yeah.
Gottfried Herold: Yeah, me too.
Gottfried Herold: The question is whether others should also be able to write on it, I guess.
Stefano: Oh, yeah, that would be… Yeah, right by remote prompting.
Antonio Sanso: Sugar option docs.
Antonio Sanso: I don't know. Let's see what is this. Again, I'm using the whiteboard all the time, so I'm…
Antonio Sanso: I'm kind of surprised that Zoom removed it.
Stefano: Actually, I don't see any difference.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah.
Gottfried Herold: Maybe it depends on the Zoom plan. Do you know who is… how you, sort of, set up the meeting?
Antonio Sanso: Depending on the pace.
Gottfried Herold: what kind of tier level of the Zoom plan it is.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, this is true as well. Let me try this. I think I can add some…
Antonio Sanso: So, up, let's see if I have to add this now. Lucid, it doesn't do a scribble.
Antonio Sanso: So let me actually do like this. I opened some notes on my computer, the notes app, and I shared that one. So I can only write myself, I guess, in that case.
Antonio Sanso: I don't know what to do.
Antonio Sanso: I'm still looking to it.
Antonio Sanso: Sure. Oh, there's some in the chat. What is that?
Antonio Sanso: Oh, oh, thanks, Matteo, let's try that, yeah.
Antonio Sanso: So I'll share the screen with that board, I guess.
Antonio Sanso: Sure.
Matteo Vena | Riva Labs: Yeah, you can share the screen, but everybody can also just click on it and you should see it happening.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah.
Antonio Sanso: Do you guys see my…
Antonio Sanso: Okay.
Matteo Vena | Riva Labs: it's.
Antonio Sanso: So how do I start a new one? How do I know? How do I write?
Matteo Vena | Riva Labs: You can just grab the pen and start, yeah.
Antonio Sanso: Sure. So, here is the idea. So, you see… you see the screen, right?
Matteo Vena | Riva Labs: Yes, we do.
Antonio Sanso: Okay, so the idea is basically like, hold on a second.
Antonio Sanso: there is, like, basically, like, you have… you have one… One user, it will have The transaction one…
Antonio Sanso: and the signature one You will put, the man pool.
Antonio Sanso: And this, yeah, will be here.
Antonio Sanso: T1.
Antonio Sanso: Signature 1… The same is going to be for another user.
Antonio Sanso: That's another signatures.
Antonio Sanso: E2… and Signature 2 I will be… oh, too much. Okay, let's see if I can go on.
Antonio Sanso: Wolfgang Wagen would be here.
Antonio Sanso: D2…
Antonio Sanso: And that's 2. So, of course, like, naively, whoever builds a block, and it will be, of course, more than 2 transactions.
Antonio Sanso: Whoever builds the block will take the transaction 1 as signature 1, transaction 2 as signature 2, and yeah, if the size of the key, the signature is too big, like it is in post-quantum case, this is going to be blowing up.
Antonio Sanso: the message, sorry, the block. So the idea with this new IP is that we have a new
Antonio Sanso: person, I knew,
Antonio Sanso: Role of aggregator. So you will have, like, here, an aggregator. I'm just, like, to be consistent, this is user one.
Antonio Sanso: This is user 2.
Antonio Sanso: So here you have an aggregator.
Antonio Sanso: And basically like when it builds the block, so aggregator and it's a block builder.
Antonio Sanso: And this is Virgin territory.
Antonio Sanso: and
Antonio Sanso: Things might change, but again, what we're trying to do for EverSensor3 is a form of this. So you have this aggregator.
Antonio Sanso: And what it does is Aggregator builds this block.
Antonio Sanso: And the block will contain only the part of the T1 without the signatures.
Antonio Sanso: The T2 without the signatures.
Antonio Sanso: And we'll call… Lean VM.
Antonio Sanso: And again, we have… Already, thanks to Emil,
Antonio Sanso: a version of LeanVM that has the parameter of the two of… of the… we ship in the…
Antonio Sanso: in the devnet, and here we'll have an aggregated signature, we'll call it SA.
Antonio Sanso: So, this is the block.
Antonio Sanso: And of course, this is going to be the block.
Antonio Sanso: Build with the transaction one, the transaction two, the aggregate signature.
Antonio Sanso: And the size of the aggregate signatures, it's actually constant. It doesn't matter if you have 100 transactions, or 10, or 200, this is going to be constant.
Antonio Sanso: So, the size of the single signatures has less impact.
Antonio Sanso: So, this is one piece of the puzzle. The other piece of the puzzle, of course, we… in the testnet, we have a Nethermind client.
Antonio Sanso: And basically, like, we need to fork it, to the verification.
Antonio Sanso: At the moment, it's using, of course, ACDSA,
Antonio Sanso: But Nethermind will come as well with an embedded version of Lean VM, so it doesn't go through a precompile, but will actually… each client will ship with a version of Lean VM, and it will call the verification of Lean VM, so when the block is going to be validated.
Antonio Sanso: is calling a version of… a version of LeanVM to verify the aggregated signatures.
Antonio Sanso: So that's in a nutshell what we are trying to do now.
Antonio Sanso: Questions?
Stefano: Yeah, what… Sorry, what do you use for the…
Stefano: What's the plan right now for the aggregation? What is the, yeah, what's the…
Matteo Vicari: For the application, yeah, it is, using Flock, and, we're for wrapping up, the proof. In LeanVM repository, you can find all.
Matteo Vicari: All, all the code for this.
Stefano: So we are wrapped flood proof.
Matteo Vicari: Yeah.
Matteo Vicari: Yeah, but again…
Antonio Sanso: This is orthogonal, we… Emil provided it, let's say, and I put a link already in the…
Antonio Sanso: Into the previous slide, so… And again, we're just users of LeanVM.
Matteo Vicari: Yeah, yeah, yeah, but the main component of LeanVM are these two.
Matteo Vicari: Yes. The basic part of LeanVM is using Flock and Wilford Wrapping Up, and then all the proofs is…
Stefano: Size of the wrap proof?
Matteo Vicari: I don't remember, sorry, I have to go.
Antonio Sanso: What's the question?
Matteo Vicari: The size of the wrap group.
Antonio Sanso: They.
Matteo Vicari: it up, yeah.
Antonio Sanso: I think it's about 200K.
Matteo Vicari: Yeah, something like this.
Stefano: Yeah.
Stefano: But that… and that's… yeah, I guess… I guess for sufficiently large signatures, that… that would be worth it.
Antonio Sanso: Exactly.
Matteo Vicari: We need more seniors work together for have an advantage. So this is why, also it's important to…
Matteo Vicari: Depends on the state of the chain, give the possibility to.
Matteo Vicari: I don't know, like, verify only one signature, if there is not much, but… We…
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, but that's…
Matteo Vicari: Yeah, it's a.
Antonio Sanso: the.
Matteo Vicari: there.
Antonio Sanso: The status of Mainnet is that you easily have signatures in a block. So, I mean, the network is… this will be a problem for a network that no one uses, but that's not the case with you, right?
Stefano: No, of course, no, no, no, I was just wondering, because, I mean, I know roughly what the… what the size of…
Stefano: Flock proofs
Stefano: is for a few thousand or tens of thousands of signatures, but I didn't look at the size of where.
Matteo Vicari: Also the Benz.
Stefano: person.
Matteo Vicari: Time you need to create the proof.
Matteo Vicari: Because, you… for now, I think it's, 20 Signador per second on a regular machine. We don't, try it on the, the node, because if the node is more power, it's more potent, so, we can aggregate more Signador per second.
Antonio Sanso: This is a really preliminary… these are really preliminary data.
Matteo Vicari: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Antonio Sanso: 20% is a number that, of course, will.
Stefano: Sorry, 20 per second is for the flock stage or for the final wrapping stage?
Matteo Vicari: Kind of wrapping, yeah.
Stefano: Okay.
Matteo Vicari: For the fire dropping.
Stefano: And…
Matteo Vicari: And also, you can do more and more, and… Yeah, bye-bye.
Antonio Sanso: These numbers are to, these numbers are really to be taken with the, with the grain of salt because it's, they're gonna improve by far. I mean, this is, we just started again, like if someone wants to be involved with, I mean.
Matteo Vicari: Yeah, we have a look, for the HeterX part for sure.
Stefano: Alright.
Matteo Vicari: The idea is, all the CHAC is doing on…
Matteo Vicari: On the, on the node.
Matteo Vicari: Okay, I also open the benchmark.
Antonio Sanso: Okay, thank you. So, tomas, okay, hello Nero, we made a prototype in the Mempool aggregation with LeanVM.
Antonio Sanso: Let me open it here. But is that about the block building or the validation, Tomas?
Antonio Sanso: So, MetaWeb, I don't know.
Tomás Grüner: Hello?
Tomás Grüner: So yeah, we're working on network leverage.
Antonio Sanso: Sorry, De.
Tomás Grüner: the.
Antonio Sanso: I didn't hear too well. Sorry for that.
Antonio Sanso: The… the mic is, doesn't work too well.
Antonio Sanso: Can you repeat that again?
Antonio Sanso: I'm looking at the PR in the meantime.
Antonio Sanso: So…
Antonio Sanso: So this is the project it tracks.
Antonio Sanso: Okay, validation. We were working on Mempool aggregation. Okay, so this is the validation.
Antonio Sanso: Okay, so, correct me if I'm wrong, you shipped this version of Atrex.
Antonio Sanso: One second, Gauthier, I'll answer quick. You shipped for Tomas, you shipped this version of ethrex with LeanVM embedded and used as a validation as well, a LeanVM validation, correct?
Antonio Sanso: In the meantime, Jens, where you got it. So, we are starting… the plan, of course, is to have a recursive aggregation, but we are starting really simple. So…
Antonio Sanso: We want to have an end-to-end to start with.
Antonio Sanso: Go, and then we'll be more ambitious in the next…
Antonio Sanso: weeks, but as long as we have a first version of AP2888,
Antonio Sanso: And then, any form of validation with the ethrex or Nethermind, we are happy, and then we can be more crazy.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, me.
Gottfried Herold: Makes sense. Makes total sense to start with the easier things first.
Antonio Sanso: So, again, this is virgin territory at the moment. I mean, we have the CIP, but so far, no one really implemented, so…
Antonio Sanso: We're trying, we're trying. So, coming back here…
Antonio Sanso: So Matteo, correct me if I'm wrong. You're you're there, let me open it. This EIP A288. Yeah EIP A288.
Antonio Sanso: So, you guys are targeting the… The 7. 7, right? So there are different test cases.
Antonio Sanso: And the guys are targeted 7.
Antonio Sanso: So, in this case, it means building a wrapper with a deep verify frame mode.
Antonio Sanso: So, this will contain…
Antonio Sanso: The depth verifier frame mode, so we will be a new frame.
Antonio Sanso: In the arbitrary, you have this.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah.
Matteo Vicari: The idea is this, and now we need to talk with Giulio for, have some clarification about the cross-verification of the other node, I can say, of the.
Matteo Vicari: The blocks, and all the rejection part, if something goes wrong during the aggregation.
Matteo Vicari: Stuff like this, yeah.
Antonio Sanso: So, but it is like the first frame will have.
Antonio Sanso: A triple with the linked string scheme, the message hash, and the public key hash.
Antonio Sanso: And then you have a verify.
Antonio Sanso: So, you have every 5… I mean, you have many of these
Antonio Sanso: How will how will actually work?
Antonio Sanso: So, you have one frame that…
Antonio Sanso: We'll link to another frame with Verify.
Antonio Sanso: Benedictine.
Antonio Sanso: Can you write on here how does it look like the frame? Maybe this helps.
Antonio Sanso: If you have a…
Matteo Vicari: Sorry, we are starting looking yesterday.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, sure, sure, sure, but I mean, just, like, how it will look like, right? Just, I mean, we have time.
Antonio Sanso: So here we'll have one frame, I will have this triple.
Antonio Sanso: And this will be like the first, the version of Lean Sphinx.
Antonio Sanso: Now let's see, let's try to figure out here, it's fun. So you have distriple, then we have message hash and public key hash.
Antonio Sanso: This is by verify frame that checks the existence of dependency with the public key hash pulled from its storage and the message hash pulled by using.
Antonio Sanso: It's pretty cryptic.
Antonio Sanso: I wish Vitalik would be here in the call.
Antonio Sanso: A transaction with a single DevPrivatePrime, Prime containing multiple… following passion
Antonio Sanso: I'm pretty confused how the test case one will actually work.
Antonio Sanso: Because, like, desktop 7 says a scenario with a mempool node, receive multiple transactions, okay, this is fine, this is what we already…
Antonio Sanso: Put in the board and wrap with recursive stark.
Antonio Sanso: All right.
Matteo Vicari: Part is done. And then we have, find a way to link the witness of every transaction in the.
Antonio Sanso: Raka.
Matteo Vicari: And the link is the LIN Sphinx scheme is, I think, is the part of the witness.
Matteo Vicari: And the message hash is… the message hash is the witness, the Linux VIN scheme, and the public hash.
Matteo Vicari: is the public key hash, I think, is just the public key.
Matteo Vicari: We need to work on this. This is a little too early for something like this. We're starting, this process.
Matteo Vicari: on the, account abstraction part, that is more easy to understand.
Matteo Vicari: And then we try to move on on the lean.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, this is really good. I was really trying to decode what this means actually. You know, this is clear to me. This is clear. This is like a version of Lean Sphinx. No problem. What is this?
Antonio Sanso: So here's the…
Matteo Vicari: This is the witness of the message, because you have… you need to have something that link the…
Matteo Vicari: The aggregation with the witness of the message.
Antonio Sanso: But what would mean in our… you know, we have a really simple use case here, right? What will be the weakness? T1 and T2?
Matteo Vicari: I think it's, something that, it's not just T1, T2, it's something you can reconstruct, look inside the proof.
Antonio Sanso: Something…
Matteo Vicari: Yeah, it's something that link the proofs.
Matteo Vicari: And the… the message.
Matteo Vicari: This is the… the…
Antonio Sanso: You know, then you want to… you want to actually… That SA is the… It's the signatures of…
Antonio Sanso: Degraded signal of T1 and T2.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah. That's what you want to prove. So…
Matteo Vicari: But also, you want to have the same anchor, I can say, on the frame.
Matteo Vicari: Because then, okay, I can have.
Matteo Vicari: This part, that's the part we need to solve better. For example, I refer all the stuff to account abstraction, because for me, it's more easy to understand.
Antonio Sanso: I mean, for me, the kind of abstraction doesn't matter, but I would really like to understand how.
Antonio Sanso: This EIP works. I mean, I really understand what this is. Message hash and public key hash.
Antonio Sanso: So… verify… okay, triple followed by a verified frame, so at least we know that here there's going to be another frame, right? So let's say this is frame 0. Do you agree this is frame 0 here?
Antonio Sanso: Here's friend 0. I said, 0.
Antonio Sanso: And here is the framework.
Antonio Sanso: Greg.
Matteo Vicari: Yeah.
Antonio Sanso: The disembodied one, right? Frame one.
Antonio Sanso: So here's the EPISA that there is a frame.
Antonio Sanso: With a single frame containing one of these triple, followed by a verify frame that checks the existence of dependency.
Antonio Sanso: With a pub key hash, so this and this are the same.
Antonio Sanso: And this and this are the same.
Antonio Sanso: bullet by using to extract the transaction. Wow, it's pretty. Yeah, it's pretty cryptic.
Antonio Sanso: This test case for transit with a single depth verified frame, not frame, but then multiple.
Antonio Sanso: Triples followed by verify frame that checks exist on dependency.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, I think we need to really spend a bit of… maybe…
Antonio Sanso: Who is the author of Vitalik and Tomas? Yeah, I need to ask them.
Antonio Sanso: Yep.
Antonio Sanso: All right. Anyway, I don't think we will be able to figure out anything here today any more than we already did.
Stefano: Can I just ask a couple of side questions since we're here?
Antonio Sanso: Sure, sure.
Stefano: What… so just to understand the number, because I'm familiar with the… with the size and behavior of the flock bash proofs for watts.
Stefano: But not for Lean Sphinx.
Stefano: How many… how many signatures?
Stefano: Typically would be aggregated in a block.
Antonio Sanso: is.
Stefano: the.
Antonio Sanso: Let's say… let's say between, I don't know, 200 to 2,000, something like this.
Stefano: Okay, so…
Antonio Sanso: Not like more or less than 1000.
Stefano: To do the 12. Below to do the 12. Below 4,000.
Matteo Vicari: The answer is… depends on the.
Matteo Vicari: On the hardware. Because, for example, if you, for aggregate.
Stefano: No, no, I mean for practical use cases. I mean, what is the target? Before we get to the… what is feasible? What would be ideally the number that we'd want to aggregate? Because I didn't look into this.
Stefano: So, a few thousand.
Antonio Sanso: No, no, a few hundreds. I mean, I don't think.
Stefano: 200.
Antonio Sanso: Hundreds, yeah, hundreds.
Stefano: Hundreds. Okay.
Antonio Sanso: No. Okay. I mean, at the moment, if you want to see how many are, you just go to Mainnet, check how many transactions are in a block in average, and that's the the number. And they're in the order of hundreds, less than a thousand.
Stefano: Okay.
Stefano: Fine. So that's subtitle. Okay. And sorry, Matteo, what was the performance on that for the flock and for the weird?
Antonio Sanso: No, I mean, the numbers that are at the moment are not the right one. I mean, at the moment, we see the really lean sphinx will be, I think, 280 per second, with the original version. With the version we forked our
Antonio Sanso: 20 per second, so it means nothing, and we're really at the beginning. But at the moment, Lean Sphinx, the one that is in Maine.
Antonio Sanso: It's about 280 per second.
Matteo Vicari: Events also on the Sphinx Parameter.
Antonio Sanso: the.
Matteo Vicari: Or the things he's doing, depends on.
Matteo Vicari: A lot of stuff.
Antonio Sanso: So.
Matteo Vicari: And depends also in the hash function you use for doing aggregation, because Flock has different.
Matteo Vicari: different results using KAC or Chateau or Blake.
Matteo Vicari: So.
Stefano: So I, for example, look, I'm asking because I know the numbers for the basic watts, essentially by heart. So I'm just trying to understand how many orders of magnitude of difference there is between verifying.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah.
Stefano: Bings versus Watts.
Antonio Sanso: example.
Stefano: So block proving for like a million signatures on, sorry, for a few hundred signature on watts is around 200 milliseconds.
Antonio Sanso: somehow.
Stefano: A second.
Antonio Sanso: For Watts, I think the target, I can't remember, Benedikt's on the call, but I think they're targeting 8,000 or 16,000 signatures, I think.
Matteo Vicari: The problem is not the verification, it's the create the proof.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, but I mean, the target.
Stefano: No, no, I'm saying proving. I'm saying proving, not verification. Proving time for what? A thousand signatures is one second.
Matteo Vicari: For now.
Stefano: 4,000 watt signatures is about…
Benedikt Wagner: 1,000 for one second.
Stefano: Yeah.
Benedikt Wagner: Do we have to…
Benedikt Wagner: Like, these improvements from OTS Golf Auto Research thing, they claim at least, at least Justin claimed something like a 4X improvement?
Matteo Vicari: Yeah, but the BENS also in the hash function do you use because.
Benedikt Wagner: Yeah.
Matteo Vicari: Yeah, there's a lot of.
Stefano: There's about a factor of 2 between Blake 3 and Shaw, and a factor of 2 between Shaw and Ketchup.
Stefano: Roughly, one point something.
Antonio Sanso: All right. Quick things. There's a message in the chat by Stefano. Thanks a lot, Stefano. So you're saying that.
Antonio Sanso: So, if you go on the chat, you see that Stefano said that, as far as understood, Lean's Sphinx scheme
Antonio Sanso: Identifies the signal scheme to use, message hash is the hash of the transaction message being authorized.
Antonio Sanso: And public hash and the public key expected to verify that signatures.
Antonio Sanso: Hmm.
Matteo Vicari: But the idea is you don't…
Matteo Vicari: The problem is you. We can't do the verification, the verifier frame on chain.
Matteo Vicari: I can say, because in this case, what you need to do is verify the proof, the Lean Sphinx proof on chain.
Matteo Vicari: And the problem to do this is hard to put on chain the verification.
Matteo Vicari: But listen.
Antonio Sanso: see.
Matteo Vicari: proofs.
Antonio Sanso: But let's assume I I know what you mean, but let's assume that you do this, you you had a smart contract that verifies, Lin's things. I I even don't understand this idea. I mean, how will it work? Like, you have the triple, and then what do you have?
Matteo Vicari: Stefano have the recent answer.
Stefano De Angelis: Hello, guys.
Antonio Sanso: Evan, can you, are you on the board? Can you write on the board? Can you write the, the, how it look like in this, in this simple case of transaction one, transaction two, the frame, the frame, the verify frame, understand.
Stefano De Angelis: I don't have access to the board, Antonio.
Antonio Sanso: So.
Matteo Vicari: There is the link on, I can send you the link.
Stefano De Angelis: Yeah, please, because I joined later, so…
Antonio Sanso: Okay, so just…
Stefano De Angelis: But the… so the high-level idea, as far as I understand, is that you have this dependency, and the dependency is describing the object being authenticated, and the way you authenticate that object, right? And then in the verify frame, you only verify that the dependency is valid.
Stefano De Angelis: So, what is declared?
Antonio Sanso: WP.
Stefano De Angelis: Pretty expected.
Antonio Sanso: Which public keys? The public key of who?
Stefano De Angelis: I think the public key is what you declare.
Matteo Vicari: one.
Stefano De Angelis: Yeah.
Stefano De Angelis: With the frame transaction.
Antonio Sanso: But who is the public key of the of who of the of the aggregator or or.
Stefano De Angelis: No, no, no, no, no. It is not confidential.
Matteo Vicari: Wallet, I think, yeah.
Stefano De Angelis: I think, I think so. It's the sender, the authorizer.
Antonio Sanso: Makes sense. And then…
Stefano De Angelis: And then you have this, in the manpool, at the manpool level, you… we have this, aggregation mechanism that is off
Stefano De Angelis: verification frame prefix. So, the prover that you're running at the mempool is the guy that is getting the, actual, artifact, which is the signature in that case.
Stefano De Angelis: From the Raptor object, which is not accessed by the frame.
Stefano De Angelis: And the wrapper object is carrying a reference to the dependency and also the signature itself. And then, since you are running the aggregator, the aggregator will verify that the wrapper object is containing the correct signature with the correct dependency that has been verified by the frame.
Stefano De Angelis: This is my high level understanding.
Antonio Sanso: Two questions. What is this that, like, in our simple case, what is message hash? It's the hash of what?
Stefano De Angelis: Of the frame transaction.
Stefano De Angelis: In this case.
Antonio Sanso: Okay, okay.
Antonio Sanso: Of the firm transaction.
Antonio Sanso: But you know, like what we are missing now is, you see in this case, like here on the, on the, on the screen, Nethermind, we are planning like to have Nethermind, being.
Stefano De Angelis: Yeah.
Antonio Sanso: Shipping with a version that will carry LeanVM or I3X as well, I mean, Nethermind, any of the client. At the moment we use Nethermind or I3X because they support Frame. So, but the idea is like to ship.
Antonio Sanso: a version of Nethermind at Rex that they ship LIMVM, and they actually extend the verification from ACDSA to as well checking the LIMVM proof. But I don't see…
Antonio Sanso: I don't see without having a precompile or a smart contract how to implement what you described.
Antonio Sanso: You know what I mean?
Antonio Sanso: Because in your case, it's really kind of required to have a smart contract or a precompile that calls
Antonio Sanso: the LeanVM verification. Does this make sense?
Stefano De Angelis: Why you need a precompile for this?
Antonio Sanso: And how is how can the the verification oh, wow.
Matteo Vicari: The smart contract is a proof that run on WIR.
Matteo Vicari: And take a lot of, really a lot of gas.
Matteo Vicari: So, This is the problem.
Matteo Vicari: I, when we start from.
Stefano: By… off the top of your head, do you know how much gas?
Antonio Sanso: I mean, I didn't check because I'm not too much interested about putting this on chain. I mean, the idea will be to really have a kind of fork of Nethermind that will do this in a native way like you do now for ECDSA.
Stefano: Yeah, sure.
Stefano De Angelis: That's… that's my understanding.
Antonio Sanso: But how can you do frame and having this native? Can you do that?
Stefano De Angelis: I think you can because of this decoupling between frame used for Verification of the syntax structure.
Stefano De Angelis: And then you have the wrapper, which is an object broadcasted on the network level, that you can access it without, outside the frames.
Antonio Sanso: Stefan, are you an expert? I've seen your name somewhere, but are you an expert of frame transaction? Who do you work for?
Stefano De Angelis: I'm not. I am researcher of Nethermind.
Antonio Sanso: Nethermind. Exactly. Great. But do you work on, on, on, on friendship?
Stefano De Angelis: So.
Antonio Sanso: Hello?
Stefano De Angelis: We, so we are being implementing frame transactions, and I am looking into A288 as next, integration in the client for…
Antonio Sanso: Because at the moment.
Stefano De Angelis: much.
Antonio Sanso: Actually, the testnet, I don't know if you've seen that we're running testnet Daisugi, and actually Giulio is, I mean, did the testnet with Nethermind. So now at the moment, this testnet is running using your stuff. I mean, the frame transaction stuff, basically.
Stefano De Angelis: Great.
Antonio Sanso: And if you have access to the board, and now there is the link on the chat, can you actually…
Antonio Sanso: Do an example, if you… at the best thoughts you can, of how you see the situation for these two transactions.
Stefano De Angelis: Try, if I can…
Antonio Sanso: Continue what? On the spotlight. But, I mean, it's just we're just trying to figure out things together. Things may help.
Stefano De Angelis: Yeah, yeah, I'm still under the exploration phase, so… It's okay. I think, Okay, let me try.
Antonio Sanso: So you can cancel my stuff. Let's let me try to cancel it.
Stefano De Angelis: Can you see what I'm doing?
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, I do actually. Yeah. Yeah. You need.
Stefano De Angelis: Okay.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, okay, so nothing.
Stefano De Angelis: From what I understand.
Stefano De Angelis: I'm going… Okay, let me open the EIP as well, so I can remember.
Stefano De Angelis: 8 to 8 to 8.
Stefano De Angelis: Hey, Pete.
Stefano De Angelis: So we're looking at test 1, right? Test case 1.
Antonio Sanso: extra.
Stefano De Angelis: Lifetime mode…
Antonio Sanso: I mean, seven, but the seven is a wrapper of one, I think.
Stefano De Angelis: So we have this guy here.
Stefano De Angelis: And then we have…
Stefano De Angelis: 35.
Stefano De Angelis: here.
Stefano De Angelis: Right, and then we have… The dependency?
Stefano De Angelis: Object.
Stefano De Angelis: Which is a triple… Was it… Lean Sphinx scheme.
Antonio Sanso: So it's Lean Sphinx, Message, and PubKey.
Stefano De Angelis: Message Ash.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah.
Stefano De Angelis: Bob click Bob key.
Stefano De Angelis: This is a triple, right? And then, in parallel to this object.
Stefano De Angelis: We have another one.
Antonio Sanso: Where's the triple? Because I don't see it. You put… okay, well, how do I… okay, I'll move it. Okay, great, I see that.
Stefano De Angelis: Can you see it?
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Antonio Sanso: Sure. So you have the lint sphinx and the lint sphinx and the message hash and the public key.
Stefano De Angelis: And this is just, like.
Antonio Sanso: Public cash, public cash.
Stefano De Angelis: Yeah, this is just a string, right?
Antonio Sanso: Yeah.
Stefano De Angelis: Then we have this object wrapper 0.
Stefano De Angelis: it defined, and I don't remember what includes, but I think it includes The message… The public key… Message…
Stefano De Angelis: Public key, and the actual signature.
Antonio Sanso: Like, what I call SICK A above.
Stefano De Angelis: I think so.
Antonio Sanso: I mean, I think I mean, I call this the aggregate signal to hear SICK A, SA. So.
Stefano De Angelis: I guess so, yes.
Stefano De Angelis: So.
Stefano De Angelis: What I think is that what happens is that here.
Stefano De Angelis: Verify that… Dependency.
Stefano De Angelis: Structure is… Valid.
Stefano De Angelis: Whatever it means.
Stefano De Angelis: But doesn't have access to the wrapper and to the signature.
Stefano De Angelis: Not very, very far.
Stefano De Angelis: Sync.
Stefano De Angelis: From Raptor.
Stefano De Angelis: And this is the frame.
Antonio Sanso: Okay.
Stefano De Angelis: Now we have in the Another mind.
Stefano De Angelis: We have another object.
Stefano De Angelis: Which is approver.
Stefano De Angelis: And please, guys, take it as a grain of salt.
Stefano De Angelis: And then here, we are actually… We have… 8288… Aggregator.
Stefano De Angelis: And this guy is consuming the wrapper.
Antonio Sanso: Do you call it aggregator or validator? I mean, it will be more validator, no? Because aggregator is very validator.
Stefano De Angelis: is basically running the circuit specified in the EIP.
Stefano De Angelis: So it's a prover.
Antonio Sanso: But it needs to verify, no? I mean…
Stefano De Angelis: Yeah, yeah, so when you aggregate, you first verify, verify the Sphinx, and then you're proving that the verification is valid.
Antonio Sanso: Yeah, but they're in two different… I mean, if you go up, there are two different phases. I mean, the aggregation happens more, at the… when the… when the… when the…
Antonio Sanso: The builder builds a block. I think that we are already at the phase where you're actually doing the verification, right?
Stefano De Angelis: I don't think it… I don't think it happens, when… only when the builder builds the block. I think it happens every one second, or every X seconds.
Antonio Sanso: Oh, sure, sure, but here, okay, you're still at the previous phase, but I think that we moved away from this phase. I mean, we were already at the verification phase, you know.
Antonio Sanso: We're… so what I'm trying to say is, like, that we…
Antonio Sanso: for the first version of the testnet, with aggregation, we are not doing it, let's say, every one second. We are happy to do the aggregation once.
Antonio Sanso: And… and that's it. And then, like, we're figuring out how to verify.
Stefano De Angelis: Okay.
Antonio Sanso: So we are looking at scenario seven.
Antonio Sanso: This case 7, and the 7 is basically, like.
Antonio Sanso: You will have, like, an aggregator that builds a block as well.
Antonio Sanso: And you build a block, and you build a block in a way that is a wrapper of test case 1.
Antonio Sanso: Okay.
Stefano De Angelis: Okay.
Antonio Sanso: So at the moment we're trying to figure out how to do the verification.
Antonio Sanso: In in Nethermind or.
Antonio Sanso: Or at racks, basically, like how to how to fork the client.
Antonio Sanso: And what you say so far makes sense to me. So you build a block that is a frame.
Antonio Sanso: And, I agree with you that
Antonio Sanso: This verifies only the dependency, but then, like, how do you actually do the verification?
Antonio Sanso: Without having access to a precompile.
Antonio Sanso: Does it make sense? Otherwise, I can explain again the flow here.
Stefano De Angelis: Maybe yes.
Stefano De Angelis: Because I didn't follow the floor.
Antonio Sanso: Do you see the… do you see the board now? Do you see it?
Stefano De Angelis: Yep.
Antonio Sanso: So basically, like, the flow is this. You have a user 1 and user 2, they have transaction 1 and signature 1, transaction 2 and signature 2.
Antonio Sanso: They both go on the mempool. And as you correctly say, there is some some kind every one second there's gonna be some some recursion happening. But we are not doing this for the beginning, we're doing only like you have one aggregator.
Antonio Sanso: That is as well as the same as a block builder in our case, that takes the two transactions, T1 and T2, it will put in a block.
Antonio Sanso: And we put transaction one, transaction two, and the aggregated signal that we call it SA. And it does in a way that it builds this block with the help of LeanVM.
Stefano De Angelis: Sorry, sorry, what is SA here?
Antonio Sanso: They aggregate the signatures. That is basically the proof of aggregation.
Stefano De Angelis: And how do you compute this proof?
Antonio Sanso: With LeanVM. We have already a fork. Can someone put in the chat the fork? We have a fork of LeanVM.
Stefano De Angelis: Okay, and the proof is proving… is just checking the two transactions.
Stefano De Angelis: And the signature of each, and then verifying those inside the… LeanVM.
Antonio Sanso: And the spitting essay that is the proof of our.
Stefano De Angelis: Yes.
Stefano De Angelis: And this is output.
Antonio Sanso: And then the aggregator gives this to the block builder, the block builder builds this block, right?
Stefano De Angelis: Right.
Stefano De Angelis: Yes.
Antonio Sanso: And then, like, this… this, the block is gonna… is gonna be, like, created, and then, like, we're trying to figure out the verification, how it will work. In our mind, it was, like, Nethermind ships with, again, with the same version of LeanVM, and in a native way.
Antonio Sanso: He will, like he's doing at the moment for ECDSA, will verify the block using
Antonio Sanso: That the the here the test case 7 and and a version of LeanVM.
Antonio Sanso: Okay, okay.
Stefano De Angelis: Now I see. Okay, so you are in the scenario where, you know, the block has been proposed, and then every other Nethermind client is receiving the block, and to verify the block is valid, they want to verify the proofs.
Antonio Sanso: mandatory.
Stefano De Angelis: Verify the proof, we don't know how to do that.
Antonio Sanso: Yes, I mean… Okay.
Stefano De Angelis: Okay.
Antonio Sanso: And this without having neither a precompile or a contract, let's say, in Solidity.
Stefano De Angelis: Yeah, so my answer to this question is that… but this is only my own understanding. Is that we will need to verify the native… to verify this proof natively inside NetherMind.
Stefano De Angelis: And this is the direction we should take, but this is not available at the moment.
Antonio Sanso: And yeah, but we can fork it. How will it.
Stefano De Angelis: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Antonio Sanso: brother.
Matteo Vicari: The verification is inside in the animals.
Stefano De Angelis: Yes.
Matteo Vicari: Then what we need is something that, link.
Matteo Vicari: The… the frame?
Matteo Vicari: And this kind of witness that allow the user to say, okay, this is verifying this way on the client, so it's good to go.
Matteo Vicari: and execute the next frame is the execution of the frame of the user. This is the stuff we are missing inside the puzzle.
Antonio Sanso: Stefano, continue your… continue your…
Antonio Sanso: your diagram there, right, that I'm showing. How will it be, in your opinion? Of course, it's not prover anymore, because we are missing the verifier, not the prover. How will… how will be a… in your opinion, how will it look like?
Stefano De Angelis: So, what I… what I was drafting here is the…
Stefano De Angelis: for the one side of the coin, where the transactions come in. Not… so the block is not built yet. That's my… for the second part, I don't think we… I have an answer for now, but I would expect.
Stefano De Angelis: to have the prover natively inside NetherMind. So we have to integrate it to verify Limbden proofs inside NetherMind.
Antonio Sanso: other.
Stefano De Angelis: Right.
Stefano De Angelis: To make it efficient.
Antonio Sanso: But I agree, actually, I don't think we're too far away from what you did. I mean, I think that the first part here stays.
Stefano De Angelis: Hill.
Antonio Sanso: Would be like in, in the prover or verifier, you will have.
Stefano De Angelis: You have…
Antonio Sanso: LeanVM and you verify, you verify that this frame actually is valid.
Stefano De Angelis: I think what you do is something like this.
Stefano De Angelis: So, this guy here…
Stefano De Angelis: Aggregate.
Stefano De Angelis: And this guy here…
Antonio Sanso: But do you agree that actually degrading we don't need? We already did degradation before.
Stefano De Angelis: Yes, yes.
Antonio Sanso: Okay.
Stefano De Angelis: But when you say we don't need, you mean we don't need…
Antonio Sanso: Yes, at a verification, because I'm.
Stefano De Angelis: Yeah.
Antonio Sanso: The aggregator is, if you're not an aggregator, I mean, there's only 1 aggregator, you don't need like
Antonio Sanso: Thousands of aggregators. You need one.
Stefano De Angelis: Yes.
Antonio Sanso: And do you think this can be done without precompile or contract, or are you actually…
Stefano De Angelis: I would… I hope so.
Antonio Sanso: Alright, let's see. Anyway, we are… in case you are… you want to participate to this effort, we are doing the version 0.3 of the testnet. Again, we are using Net of Mind, so…
Antonio Sanso: If you're interested, I will add you to the testnet Telegram group.
Stefano De Angelis: Yes, please.
Stefano De Angelis: Yes, please. Also, because we are scoping for.
Stefano: Yeah.
Stefano De Angelis: know, Implementing all the missing dots.
Stefano De Angelis: Inside Nethermind, so I would like to… to join.
Antonio Sanso: All right. Have you already seen Daisuki.fk?
Stefano De Angelis: Yes.
Antonio Sanso: Okay.
Antonio Sanso: Perfect. And there are, again, we are up to, we're up to frame transaction. Again, we are missing only the, only, I mean.
Antonio Sanso: The heavy part. We're missing the aggregation part, so let's wait.
Stefano De Angelis: Okay.
Antonio Sanso: Alright.
Stefano De Angelis: Great.
Antonio Sanso: Cool. I think we're almost at time. I'm sure we're going to make it. We just need to figure out some details. Maybe in one of the next calls, I will try to bring in Vitalik or Tomas that are the author of the EIP.
Antonio Sanso: But hopefully for the next two weeks, we're gonna have more
Antonio Sanso: Clear mind on how all this work, yeah.
Stefano De Angelis: I would also be happy to bring for the next call a concrete solution to the problem, having test case 7 as a
Stefano De Angelis: You know, objectives.
Antonio Sanso: Perfect. Again, let's move to the testnet.
Antonio Sanso: Telegram chat, I will add you right after the call, right?
Stefano De Angelis: Nice. Perfect.
Antonio Sanso: Cool.
Antonio Sanso: And yeah, and anyone, if anyone else wants to help out on the testnet, let me know.
Antonio Sanso: I'm in Telegram, and yeah, I will add you as well.
Antonio Sanso: I think we're almost at time, it was a bit different today, sorry for hijacking a bit the call, but yeah, we need to figure out how to bring this further, right?
Antonio Sanso: Cool. Thanks a lot for everyone participating, and I'll see you in two weeks.
Stefano De Angelis: Thank you.
Stefano: Santhani.
Matteo Vicari: you.
Alessandro Baiocchi: Thank you. See you, Anthony.
Alessandro Baiocchi: See you.